<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anabaptism considered Wherein the chief objections of that sect against infant-baptism, and the manner of baptizing by aspersion, or sprinkling, are fairly stated and answered; and reasons given why dipping is not to be taken as the essential or necessary mode of administration. In a familiar letter of advice to a parishioner inclining that way. By William Eratt, M.A. and minister of Hatfield near Doncaster.</title>
            <author>Eratt, William, 1655 or 6-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 87 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38578</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200374</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825059</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29431</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38578)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29431)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2090:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anabaptism considered Wherein the chief objections of that sect against infant-baptism, and the manner of baptizing by aspersion, or sprinkling, are fairly stated and answered; and reasons given why dipping is not to be taken as the essential or necessary mode of administration. In a familiar letter of advice to a parishioner inclining that way. By William Eratt, M.A. and minister of Hatfield near Doncaster.</title>
                  <author>Eratt, William, 1655 or 6-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by W.B. for A. and J. Churchill. And for Robert Clark in York,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCC. [1700]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bamburgh Castle Library, University of Durham, Durham, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29431:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29431:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANABAPTISM CONSIDERED.</p>
            <p>Wherein the chief Objections of that Sect againſt Infant-Baptiſm, and the manner of Baptizing by Aſperſion, or Sprinkling, are fairly ſtated and anſwered;</p>
            <p>AND REASONS given why Dipping is not to be taken as the eſſential or neceſſary Mode of Adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In a familiar Letter of Advice to a Pariſhioner incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>William Eratt,</hi> M. A. and Miniſter of <hi>Hatfield</hi> near <hi>Doncaſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Gal. 4.16, 17.</hi>
                  </bibl> Am I therefore become your enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth? they zealouſly affect you, but not well.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 14.15.</hi>
                  </bibl> The ſimple believeth every word, but the prudent man looketh well to his going.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. B.</hi> for <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>J. Churchill.</hi> And for <hi>Robert Clark</hi> in <hi>York.</hi> MDCC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:29431:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29431:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Neighbour Woodward,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Muſt needs ſay (and complain too) you have been unjuſt to your ſelf, and unkind to me as your Miniſter, in not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me worthy of being conſulted in your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Concerns, (as to which I am given to underſtand, you have lately been under ſome Scruples, doubting of the Truth of your former Profeſſion in the Communion of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and ſeeming to incline to the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Perſuaſion.) Now to ſet you at rights herein, the Errand of this is to acquaint you, that I look upon it as a Duty incumbent upon me, to give you the beſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I can (though not deſired) in this your grand Affair, the Welfare of your Soul.</p>
            <p>Pray then, let not the Length of my Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affright you, for it is honeſtly intended for your good; and I hope it will prove ſo,
<pb facs="tcp:29431:3"/>be but you as eaſie and ſincere in the Peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal as I was in the Writing of it: And if my little pains taken herein do but ſatisfie your Scruples, and bring you home to our Mother the Church, from whence you were unadviſedly ſtraying, I ſhall think my ſelf plentifully rewarded, who am, without Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your loving Friend and Miniſter,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan. 9. 1699/700.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Eratt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:29431:3"/>
            <head>ANABAPTISM CONSIDERED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>J. W.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am apt to think, your raſh ſeparating your ſelf from the Church wherein you were baptized and bred up, is a Caſe, when well examined, you will not eaſily anſwer, either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God or Man, for all the new Light you ſo much (as I hear) now boaſt of; for as our Saviour ſpeaks in the Goſpel, <hi>If the light that is in thee be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 6.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You are pleas'd to ſay, you have been hitherto in Errour and Darkneſs; but however that be, are you now infallibly ſure of your being in the right way? This Principle of Popiſh Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (I preſume) you will hardly pretend to, for that ſavours too much of the blind Zeal and Enthuſiaſm of <hi>Ignatius Loyola</hi> the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> If then 'tis poſſible for a Man to be miſtaken (though himſelf believes otherwiſe) and if Zeal does not always prove the beſt cauſe; for as St.
<note place="margin">Rom. 10.2.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> affirms of ſome of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> that they had a Zeal of God, but not according to Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; from hence then I gather, there may be an erroneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that is, a Man may be zealouſly affected in an ill matter.</p>
            <p>Not to inſtance herein Examples of former Times, we have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern ones ſufficient.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the Caſe of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> they're infallibly ſure of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the right, and all others in the wrong; and that there is no Salvation out of the Communion of their Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to the <hi>Quakers,</hi> they are as confident of their way, that they are inwardly taught of God by his Spirit; and yet, I dare ſay, for all the Zeal of the one; or the other, you will eaſily agree with me, they are both groſly miſtaken in matters of Religion and Religious Worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29431:4"/>
            <p>From what has been ſaid, I thus argue; That a confident Zeal is not always an Aſſurance of Truth being there; and (this premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) give me leave to tell you what a Lover of Truth ought to do, ſuppoſe he has ſome Scruples upon him that he has been in a wrong way. In this Caſe, a ſcrupulous Conſcience ſhou'd take eſpecial care to inform it ſelf theſe two ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Examine into the Validity of thoſe Scruples that ſeem to diſuade him from the Profeſſion he has lived in.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If after all his Searches after Truth, his Scruples do ſtill grow upon him, and he cannot ſatisfie himſelf to continue in his former Profeſſion; in the next place, a Wiſe-man, and a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Chriſtian, ſhou'd by all due ways and means examine into the truth and ſafety of the new way he intends to make choice of; elſe, though the way he has been in (as he fancies) is not good, yet ſo may it fall out, he may take a worſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, A prudent Chriſtian, who is a Lover of Truth, ſhou'd by all due ways and means examine into the Validity of thoſe Scruples that ſeem to diſſuade him from the Profeſſion he has li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in. Inconſtancy, in any one, argues a Weakneſs, inſomuch that the Wiſe man urgeth us,
<note place="margin">Prov. 24.21.</note> 
               <hi>not to meddle with them that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to change;</hi> and 'tis excellent Advice which the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives,
<note place="margin">Heb. 10.23.</note> to <hi>hold faſt the profeſſion of our Faith without wavering.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle begs of <hi>Roman</hi> Converts, to beware of fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thoſe who occaſion Schiſms or Diviſions in the Church of God;
<note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>I beſeech you, Brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences contrary to the doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now who thoſe are who have always been for dividing the Members of Chriſt's Body, hear the Character of them given, the 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6, 7. <hi>Of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women laden with ſins, led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To bring the Matter home to our preſent purpoſe, you ſee how dangerous a thing it is to be guilty of Hereſie or Schiſm. If you had then been a Lover of Truth and of Peace, you ought firſt to have conſulted me as your Miniſter, and laid before me your Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, e'er you had openly diſſented from the Communion of the Church. You ought to ſhew me from the holy Scriptures, the Standard of Truth, wherein the Terms of our Communion are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29431:4"/>what Doctrines they are our Church maintains and teaches, which are contrary to the Word of God. Will you try and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Church you have been baptiz'd and brought up in, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hearing what ſhe has to ſay for her ſelf? It is againſt the Law of Nations to condemn any Perſon <hi>(indictâ cauſâ)</hi> before his Cauſe is heard: and to caution you by the way, you are to be very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in your enquiry of the Doctrines taught in the Sacred Writ, and not to paſs your Judgment raſhly in favour of this or that Opinion in contradiction to the received Doctrines and conſtant Practice of the Church of God ſince the time of Chriſt and his Apoſtles; for I muſt tell you, that the worſt of Hereticks, in all Ages, have plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Scripture in behalf of their Erroneous Principles: the <hi>Socinians,</hi> the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> the <hi>Deiſts,</hi> and the very <hi>Atheiſts</hi> themſelves, have ſomething to alledge out of Holy Writ in the defence of their naughty Cauſe. Now how this comes to paſs, St. <hi>Peter</hi> gives us to underſtand, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. that <hi>the unlearned and unſtable do wreſt the holy Scriptures to their own deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I beg of you therefore for Chriſt's ſake, and for your own Soul's ſake, not to be of the number of thoſe who are, as the Apoſtle affirms,
<note place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>Children toſſed to and fro with every wind of doctrine by the ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſs whereby they lye in wait to deceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis a hard matter to think you ſhou'd have liv'd to theſe years and yet have your Religion to ſeek: the meaning of Religion is, to bind us up to the performance of our Duty towards God and towards Man; and in this reſpect our Church is not wanting in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſufficient Rules and Directions, do we but follow them; and if we do not, 'tis our own faults, not the Churches. In this way you have been brought up, and herein Chriſtian prudence doth oblige you to continue, till you be aſſured of a better, and ſhewn where it is; and that falls next under our Conſideration: Namely,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That a prudent Chriſtian ſhou'd not upon ſome nice Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples forſake the Religion he has been brought up in, until he has Aſſurance given of a better: and no prudent Man would change for the worſe. <hi>All is not Gold that gliſters.</hi> We ought to try before we truſt: and he muſt be a very weak Man that will change his Religion at the firſt ſight of another offered in its ſtead, before he has examin'd the Truth of it.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the matter in hand, you are perſuaded to leave the Communion of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and to join with the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29431:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and why? For Conſcience ſake, you ſay, that way being, as you think, the better, and the more for your Soul's health: But then there ſhou'd go two words to a Bargain; and 'tis but common Prudence and Juſtice to your old Religion, to examine wherein the new one is better. Now to put you in a right way of Examination, the Queſtion will be, Wherein is your new Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion better then my old Profeſſion? The Anſwer, according to Scripture and Reaſon, is, it is purer in Doctrine, Diſcipline, and Worſhip.</p>
            <p>But then we muſt go on to Particulars, and Examine from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Reaſon the Truth of the matter. Now I do ſay, it lies upon you to ſhew me, wherein the Purity of this new way excels the old one in the aforementioned reſpects, and you are to keep to your old way till that be done: And this, in the name of God and Chriſt, I demand of you to do, as you will Anſwer the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary at the great Tribunal. You are oblig'd hereto upon two ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts;</p>
            <p n="1">1. With regard to your own Soul, ſhould this new way prove a falſe one.</p>
            <p n="2">2. With regard to the Souls of others, who may be led into Errour by your Example.</p>
            <p>I ſhall be glad to have your anſwer, and deſire that it may be in the Spirit of meekneſs, as coming from one who ſeeks after the Truth, and (when found) is willing to embrace the ſame and to ſtand to it: Our Church has ſtill the beſt right to you. You have not as yet, I hope, renounced your Baptiſm, and the true Mother will not agree with the Harlott to divide; but if you are reſolved right or wrong to forſake the Church, at leaſt do not abuſe her: Pray then let your anſwer be modeſt and free from Cavil.</p>
            <p>Now I muſt needs tell you, that did I doubt of the way I am in (as I thank God I do not) of all the ſeveral Perſuaſions among Chriſtians the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would be fartheſt from my thoughts of joyning to, and that for theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. With reſpect to thoſe Perſons who were the firſt Broachers of this Sect in the City of <hi>Munſter</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> about the Year of our Lord 1533. <hi>viz. John Matthias, Jo. Buckhold (alias Jo.</hi> of <hi>Ieyden) Mancer, Knipper-dolling, Nicholas Stokins, Knippen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> and others, their firſt Reformers, whoſe Perſuaſion was founded in Blood; they raiſed a Sedition in the City, ſeized of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29431:5"/>the Magiſtrates, degraded the Senate, and ſet up their own Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders, plunder'd all places ſacred and profane. <hi>John Matthias</hi> being kill'd in a Skirmiſh, <hi>Knipperdoling</hi> pretended a Revelation, that <hi>Buckhold</hi> muſt be exalted to royal Dignity, and to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Throne of his Father <hi>David;</hi> and having his <hi>Regalia</hi> put on him, he had a Throne built him in the Market-place, and was called the King of Juſtice, and of the <hi>New Jeruſalem. Buckhold</hi> openly, before the People, made a mock Sacrament, gave every one an unleavened Loaf, ſaying, <hi>Take, eat, and celebrate the Lord's death.</hi> He had three Wives, which were called his Queens; one of which, who had been a Glover's Wench, happening to offend him, he ſtruck off her Head in the Market-place, charging her with Adultery: in the mean time his other two pretended Queens ſung a blaſphemous Hymn, beginning with <hi>Glory be to God on high.</hi> Whilſt theſe wicked Reformers were for two years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carrying on their ſeditious and baſe Deſigns, ſeveral thouſand Souls periſhed in the City by Famine and the Sword: but I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſaying any more of thoſe ſad Varlets, thoſe lewd Reformers, who never learn'd this way of reforming from Chriſt or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. And now let us ſee what Doctrines they taught. And can we expect to gather Grapes of Thorns, or Figs of Thiſtles?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then with reſpect to their Doctrines: they taught, that Chriſt was not the true God; that we are righteous by our own Merits and Sufferings; that there is no original Sin; that Infants are not to be baptized; they maintained Poligamy, that a Man may put away his Wife if of another Religion; that the Godly ſhould enjoy a Monarchy upon Earth; and that any Man may Preach and give the Sacraments. Theſe and ſuch like were their pernicious and fulſome Doctrines, which 'tis a ſhame to mention amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>To all this I expect as ſhort an Anſwer as was given lately to the Reverend Mr. <hi>Weſley</hi>'s Book of the Sacraments, by one of that Party at <hi>Epworth, It is all Lies:</hi> But if the Truth hereof be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, I can bring in a cloud of Writers of that time in teſtimony of what has been ſaid, of ſeveral Nations and ſeveral Perſuaſions. If they are now aſhamed of ſome of their Primitive Doctrines, I'm glad of it; but however, hence I think I may juſtly infer, that if the Fountain-head of this Sect was ſo corrupt, the Streams flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thence cannot be very pure: And it muſt be ſuppoſed an into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable foul way I was in, ſhould I leave it to follow thoſe Men.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29431:6"/>
            <p n="3">3. With reſpect to the preſent way of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their Diſputes, I ſhould not be very inclinable to be of that Perſuaſion; for their uſual way is; to ſpeak or write more againſt their Adverſaries, than in the Merits of their own Cauſe: And this to me ſeems an Argument of a bad one, when a Man by way of Subterfuge is forc'd to fly in his Adverſaries face, when he has little to ſay in his own defence: And for once the Party muſt not take it ill if I ſerve 'em in their own ſawce. Well then,</p>
            <p>I muſt ask them, How they can, with any face of Authority, call themſelves a Church? for, pray whence had they their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery? for, as the Apoſtle argues <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>How ſhall they call on him in whom they have not believed? and how ſhall they believe in him on whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Preacher? and how ſhall they preach except they be ſent?</hi> and in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.4. the ſame Apoſtle declares, with reſpect to the Miniſterial Function, that <hi>no man taketh this honour to himſelf but he that is called of God, as was Aaron.</hi> 'Tis plain our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour firſt choſe twelve Apoſtles, and gave 'em Power, by Prayer, and Impoſition of hands, to ordain others after them for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the ſeveral Orders and Offices in the Church to all future Ages. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>And he gave ſome Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers;</hi> and for what end, we are given to underſtand in the next Verſe, <hi>viz. for the perfecting the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt.</hi> And the three Miniſterial Orders of Biſhops, Prieſts (or Presbyters) and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, ſo often mentioned in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, have been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily preſerved in the Church ever ſince the time of the Apoſtles, and were rightfully and lawfully continued in the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> at the time of our Reformation from Popery.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But pray then, Where had the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Ordaining Miniſters? Who gave the Laity the right of Impoſition of hands, to Ordain Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons?</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Anſwer is (I'll warrant you) <hi>They have an inward Call of God.</hi> This is plainly <hi>Buckhold</hi> and <hi>Knipperdoling.</hi> And thus far however they will own their firſt Reformers.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29431:6"/>
            <p>At this rate they may have as many Teachers as People; for every one that has but enough of Confidence or blind Zeal, may ſet up when he will, his Call is good. But I wiſh ſuch Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders wou'd conſider the Danger of offering ſtrange Incenſe, and alſo what befel <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for uſurping the Prieſt's Office (<hi>Numb.</hi> 16.10, 31, 32.)</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> And now I'm doing, I muſt ask 'em another Queſtion or two: If they have no lawful Miniſters, where is their lawful Miniſtery? and then, Where are their Sacraments, if they have not proper Perſons to adminiſter them?</q>
            <p>And now, my Friend, the Conſideration of this matter alone, would ſufficiently ſtartle and keep me off from going to this Sect, which is, in deed and in truth, according to the Doctrine of our Saviour and his Apoſtles, no Church at all.</p>
            <p>Pray then, good Neighbour, be not ſo conceitedly fooliſh as to ſtrain at a Gnat and ſwallow a Camel. And thus I've paid 'em in their own Coyn, hoping that hereafter they'll let our Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; for they have work enough at home, if they will but look to it, to keep their own Houſe clean, they having neither Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline, nor Worſhip (as matters are with them) tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtolical. If what has been ſaid will not diſſuade you from running after thoſe People, I ſhall however have the inward Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of doing my Duty, as the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 19. <hi>Since I have given you warning, if you die in your Sins</hi> (as doubtleſs Hereſie is a grievous one) <hi>your blood muſt lye at your own door.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> I think I might conclude, having already exceeded the uſual Limits of a Letter. But foraſmuch as the matter I'm upon is the Cauſe of God and of Truth, is concerning the Welfare of your Soul, and the Peace of my dear Pariſhioners; I hope you'll excuſe me if I go on farther, and examine ſome Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections made by the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> againſt our Mother the Church; for I would not willingly leave one Stone in your way, that ſhould in the leaſt make you ſtumble in your Return home to that Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith you have been brought up in, which is built upon the Doctrines of the Apoſtles, Chriſt Jeſus being the chief Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner-ſtone.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:29431:7"/>
            <p>The chief Objections then of our Adverſaries (for ſo I muſt term them ſo long as they prevaricate with the Goſpel of Chriſt) are chiefly two, which they ſeem the moſt to inſiſt on in proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lvting or gaining Diſciples: both theſe concern the Sacrament of Baptiſm.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 1. That we are miſtaken in the Subjects of Baptiſm, in baptizing of Infants.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> 2. That we are wrong in the manner of Adminiſtration, in ſprinkling inſtead of dipping.</p>
            </q>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak to theſe two Objections ſeverally; but foraſmuch as my Letter is ſwoln already too big, if therefore my Anſwer herein proves not ſatisfactory (as being too brief) give your par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Reaſons of your Diſſatisfaction; and if they're not already anſwered, by the Aſſiſtance of Almighty God, you ſhall not long want another Anſwer to ſuch Objections as you ſhall make (if of any weight or moment,) wherein I ſhall argue the matter with you more at large.</p>
            <p>I begin with their firſt Objection, theirs I ſay, not yours; for you do the Cauſe of your Mother the Church great wrong, ſhould you be on the offenſive ſide, when you ought to be on the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive; 'twould be even unnatural to arraign her, when you ought to plead in her behalf; to join and engage your ſelf with the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Party, when in Duty and Prudence you ſhould ſtand againſt it: for what will all your Brethren, my Pariſhioners, and all other indifferent Perſons, ſay of you, ſhou'd you ſo ſhamefully give up the Cauſe (wherein both your Conſcience and your Credit are concern'd) before the ſame is fairly heard and try'd. But I muſt go on with the Objection; and as they put it, the ſtrength of it lies in theſe two things, That there ought to be Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance before Baptiſm: the one, ſay they, Children cannot have, the other they cannot perform, and ſo are not capable of receiving this Ordinance. Now to ſet the matter in queſtion in a true light, I ſhall examine the two Branches of the Objections ſeparately.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to Faith, I anſwer, If thereby they mean an actual or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion of Faith is neceſſary in Children before they can receive the ſign of the Covenant, this I deny, and it lies upon them
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29431:7"/>to prove it; but then I affirm, that Children of believing Parents have ſuch
<note n="*" place="margin">I mean an outward or foederal Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, ſuch as the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Children had.</note> an imputed Righteouſneſs of Faith as is requiſite to entitle them to the initiating Covenant, and ſo have a right to the Sign or Seal of that Covenant, namely, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> whereby they're diſcipled or initiated into the Chriſtian Profeſſion, and ſo are made viſible Members of Chriſt's Church. But for the farther clearing of this point, let us compare
<note n="†" place="margin">Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion <hi>and</hi> Baptiſm <hi>are Seals of the ſame Evangelical Covenant; the former given by God to</hi> Abraham, <hi>the latter given by Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </note> Circumciſion and Baptiſm toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they reſpect thoſe two things; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Matter of Fact.</item>
                  <item>2. Matter of Right.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now it cannot be denied but Circumciſion was the Seal of the
<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Of the promiſed</hi> Meſſiah <hi>to our Father</hi> Abraham <hi>who was to come.</hi>
               </note> Evangelical Covenant; and was not that a Covenant of Faith? yea, doubtleſs. We have the Authority of St. <hi>Paul</hi> for it, who calls it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. the <hi>Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith.</hi> And were not (I pray you) Children capable of receiving this Seal of Faith given to <hi>Abraham?</hi> You anſwer, Yes: tell me then why not Children of Believers now? or were Infants under the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more capable of receiving the Seal of Faith then, than Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are now under the Goſpel? or was the Seal of this firſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Faith more privilegial and extenſive in favour to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam</hi> and his natural Seed, than the ſecond Seal of the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is in and through Chriſt to all thoſe who are of the Faith of <hi>Abraham?</hi> Who will preſume to affirm this?</p>
            <p>I'm not ignorant what a Noiſe the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> make about the Commiſſion our Saviour gave his Apoſtles in reference to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſm; <hi>Go teach all Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>Baptizing them in the Name of,</hi> &amp;c. They'll tell you, Perſons muſt be taught before they are baptiz'd; but with their Favour, this is not always to be taken in their meaning, but only in the caſe of adult Perſons.</p>
            <p>For if we conſider the Etymology and real Signification of the Word <hi>Teach,</hi> in the Original it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which according to very learned Expoſitours, ſignifies alſo diſcipling: and then the Commiſſion runs thus, <hi>Go ye, and by Baptiſm make diſciples.</hi> To what end? That they may be taught and inſtructed in the Duties of the Chriſtian Faith; as will plainly appear if you take the Commiſſion mentioned in the 19th ver. together with what follows in the 20th: and it is thus, <hi>Go ye, Diſciple all Nations,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29431:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, Teaching 'em to obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you.</hi> They'll anſwer, we are only for the lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Senſe of the Word. I reply, diſcipling is alſo as true a mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word, if the Original muſt be judge; but if they do not underſtand it, or will not believe it, I cannot help that.</p>
            <p>And now that we are upon Chriſt's Commiſſion, let us examine it a little farther, as to the extent of it—<hi>Go ye, Baptize all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> &amp;c. Ask'em what this means, and then they're againſt the literal Meaning; for we ſay this Authority muſt needs reach the Baptiſm of Infants, if Children are part of the World; and there cannot be all Nations, if they are excluded. No ſuch matter, ſay they; this Commiſſion extends only to adult Perſons of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who are firſt to be taught, and then to be baptized. When we urge farther that of the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter, The promiſe is to you and your children;</hi> they anſwer as before, This is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to you and your Poſterity, as when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is meant all Perſons of that Stock: and if we agree to this, how then? Are not young Children (I pray ye) part of that Stock? Truly there are not many Families in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon without them; and if it was otherwiſe, there would ſoon be left but few, or no Nations at all.</p>
            <p>From the extent of the Commiſſion, let us go the Execution of it, and ſee if that can help to reconcile us. Well then, from Scripture we tell'em of whole Families that were Baptized to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as <hi>Lydia</hi> and her houſhould, the Jayler of <hi>Philippi,</hi> he and all his ſtraitway, and how St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms that he baptized the houſhould of <hi>Stephanas</hi> (1 Cor. 1.16.) And are they ſure there were no Children in theſe Families.</p>
            <p>But farther, there is one thing more I muſt obſerve unto you before I leave the Authority of the Scriptures as to this point; that there were three ways of Proſelyting among the <hi>Jews,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Circumciſion, Baptiſm, and Sacrifice: The firſt belonged only to the Males, the two latter to all, Men, Women, and Children; and all the Rabbins do with one coment affirm, that Perſons of all Ages and Sexes were admitted into the Church by Baptiſm: In the <hi>Gemara</hi> it is thus expreſſed: <hi>If with a Proſelyte his Sons and his Daughters are made Proſelytes alſo, that which is done by their Father redounds to their good: and again in the Babylonian Talmud, They baptize a little Proſelyte</hi> according to the Judgment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29431:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anhedrim;</hi> that is, as the Gloſs renders it. If he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his Father, and his Mother brings him to be proſelyted, he is baptiz'd according to the Cuſtom; which was this, there was to be three Men preſent at his Baptiſm who were accepted inſtead of a Father to him.</p>
            <p>From hence I obſerve, That the Cuſtom of Baptiſm being a thing ſo common among the <hi>Jews</hi> when they ſent Meſſengers to <hi>John,</hi> the Queſtion was not, <hi>Why doſt thou baptize?</hi> which in all likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood had been the firſt Queſtion, had not Baptiſm, with them been ſo uſually a way of diſcipling; no, but they demand the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Baptizer, and they asked him and ſaid unto him, <hi>Why baptizeſt thou then, if thou be not the Chriſt, nor Elias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1 25.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence alſo I farther obſerve, that <hi>Pedobaptiſm</hi> being ſo common and known a Cuſtom in the Jewiſh Church, when Multitudes flock'd to <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm, who dare poſitively affirm they did not bring their Children along with them to be baptized? As to our Adverſaries alledging, where is it ſaid, <hi>Go, Baptize Infants?</hi> I anſwer, What need was there to ſtrengthen Baptiſm with any particular Precept, when it became an Evangelical Sacrament? for that our Saviour took it as he found it, this only added, that he promoted it to a more worthy End, and to a larger Uſe, to be a Seal of the Covenant of Faith, as Circumciſion was before; and to be alſo the Laver of Regeneration, not only to the Natural Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but to all thoſe who ſhould be of the Faith of our Father <hi>Abraham;</hi> and that there is in ſome Meaſure
<note n="*" place="margin">An out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deral Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</note> an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted righteouſneſs of Faith as well as an actual one, ſeems to me very plain from St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when he thus argues, <hi>The unbelieving husband is ſanctified by the wife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>and the unbelieving wife by the husband, elſe were your children unclean, but now are they holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot tell what can be meant by this Holineſs, but that the
<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Theſe</hi> (neceſſitate co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente) <hi>may have private Baptiſm; but the other, I think, cannot without Sponſors be admitted viſible Members of Chriſt's Church.</hi>
               </note> Children of believing Parents have a Right and Privilege to the Seal of the Covenant above thoſe of Unbelievers, namely to Baptiſm, which the Apoſtle calls the Laver of Regeneration; and this new Birth muſt ſuppoſe a great advantage redounding to them by receiving this Sacrament: and for this I refer you to our Church's Explanation herein touching Baptiſm, That it is <hi>an outward viſible Sign of an inward ſpiritual Grace, given unto us, ordained by Chriſt himſelf, as a means whereby we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29431:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>receive the ſame, and as a Pledge to aſſure us thereof; and that being by Nature born in Sin, and the Children of Wrath, we are hereby made the Children of Grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this add the Common uſage in the Church of executing this our Lord's Commiſſion ever ſince the Apoſtles days, in all Nations and Countries where the Goſpel hath ſpread it ſelf: and whether the baptizing of Infants has not been the received Doctrine and Practice of all the Churches in general (whether Eaſtern or Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern) I appeal herein to the unanimous conſent of the Ancient Fathers; and the ſame is yet (for any thing I have either read or heard) the Cuſtom of all National Churches in the whole Chriſtian World to this very day: and if we ſhould ſpeak of ſingle Chriſtians (on which I lay no other ſtreſs than to diſcover the preſumptuous Confidence of our Adverſaries) the Number of thoſe who are for <hi>Pedobaptiſm,</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> is as much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity (I believe I may affirm) as ten thouſand Men are to one. And ſo much as to matter of Fact.</p>
            <p>In the next place, we come to matter of Right; and I hope, Neighbour, we need not ſtand long upon this; for where matter of Fact is by divine injunction, in the ſame or in a parallel Caſe, matter of Right cannot be diſputed without reflecting upon the Authority of the Lawgiver or Commander. To come then to an iſſue in this Point, you have heard that the command is general, <hi>Go, Baptize all Nations;</hi> and that Children muſt be taken as part of that All: and in general Laws the relating of particulars is not required, becauſe Laws always paſs on the whole kind, and a part muſt neceſſarily be ſuppoſed to be included in the whole, as a particular in an Univerſal.</p>
            <p>Beſides, I judge the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> themſelves are of this opinion in the caſe of the other Sacrament, the <hi>Lord's Supper:</hi> elſe why do they admit Women to it? We own, 'tis true, that all ought to celebrate the Lord's Death; but I ask, Where is it particularly commanded that Women are to receive as well as Men? Our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries in this caſe muſt clear it thus; They are part of Mankind, Perſons for whom Chriſt died as well as Men, and ſo are within our Lord's general Precept, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> I take this as a good Anſwer. But then,</p>
            <p>I ask them, Why is not the Command in the initiating Seal to be lookt upon as extenſive as it is (they being Judges) in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming Pledge or Seal? It muſt needs be as general (with regard
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29431:9"/>to the Precept) elſe ſome Perſons might receive the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per before they're baptized, and ſo their Confirmation in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith might in order of Time precede their Initiation, and thoſe might be admitted Gueſts at the Lord's Table, who never were really his Diſciples; which none, I think, will allow, that own the Sacraments. And thus it ſeems plain to me that it muſt needs follow, if Children are included in the general Precept of Baptiſm, then they ought of right to be baptized; for in every Law of God there muſt be ſuppoſed a Reaſonableneſs and Equity in the Performance, becauſe every ſuch Law is the Sanction of Truth and Juſtice, in as much as the ſame is enacted by an all-wiſe Lawgiver.</p>
            <p>But here is another Objection thrown in my way, and I fear <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> you'll not let me go on, till 'tis removed; and 'tis this.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> Say our Adverſaries, Now we'll fight you with your own Weapons; If the Law of the two Sacraments be general, and the one as extenſive as the other, why is not the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per given to Infants as well as to Men and Women?</q>
            <p>I anſwer, For very good Reaſons 'tis moſt convenient and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that Children as well as adult Perſons, be baptized, that ſo Chriſt's Flock may be diſtinguiſht from <hi>Jews, Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Pagans;</hi> and it ſhews a wonderful kind Love in our Saviour in bringing thoſe Infants (in whom there is no actual let or hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their own) nearer unto him, by his gracious Ordinance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Baptiſm, wherein he ſets his Seal that <hi>of ſuch is the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> And I the rather believe this, for that when our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was on Earth he manifeſted ſuch Love and perſonal Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for them even as a Father, his Words and Actions were both full of Affections towards them; <hi>He took them up in his arms,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>put his hands upon them, and bleſſed them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add to this, That we are all conceived and born in Sin; and that <hi>as in Adam all dy'd,</hi> how then?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſo in Chriſt all ſhould be made alive,</hi> that is <hi>(Salvabiles)</hi> ſavable (1 Cor. 15 22.) and without all doubt Children are a part of this All, for whom Chriſt dyed and roſe again. Now this being ſo, and there being no other means that we know of in an ordinary way, but Baptiſm, whereby Children have the Grace of the Covenant convey'd unto them, that being
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29431:10"/>the outward Seal thereof, and that being alſo the Laver of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation wherein the Stain of Original Sin is waſhed away.</p>
            <p>This then implies a neceſſity of their being baptized; and this Doctrine our Saviour himſelf confirms, when he ſaith, <hi>John</hi> 3.5. <hi>Except a man be born of water and of the Spirit, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven. Except a Man,</hi> here muſt be meant all the Kind of Man, elſe may Women be excluded as well as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. Thus 'tis moſt reaſonable Children ſhould be baptized. But then,</p>
            <p>As to the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, the caſe is far diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; the Reaſon of the thing ſhews that there is a great diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to be made 'twixt a Diſciple or one that is newly entred a Scholar in Chriſt's School, and thoſe who are come to ſome growth and ſtature in the Chriſtian Profeſſion: in young Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners a tractable Diſpoſition or Inclination to learn is accepted; whereas in adult Perſons, becauſe more is given ſo more is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of them; they come to the Lord's Table to renew their bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal Vow, and to ſet forth the Lord's Death; they are Gueſts invited, bid to prepare themſelves, and therefore 'tis expected they put on the Wedding-garment: they muſt go thither with actual Faith and Obedience; they muſt call themſelves to account; and, as our Church piouſly admoniſhes ſuch, <hi>They are to examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves whether they truly repent them of their former Sins, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly purpoſing to lead a new Life, having a lively <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith in God's mercy through Chriſt, with a thankful Remembrance of his Death, and to be in charity with all men.</hi> So that whether we reſpect the Conditions qualifying a worthy Communicant, or the end of his receiving, that Duty cannot be expected from babes, but from thoſe who are Proficients, are grown up in the Knowledge and Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. And this I hope you will take as a ſufficient Anſwer to this Objection: and we may therefore go on. Having then ſhewn, both from matter of Fact, and matter of Right, that Infants ought to be baptized, let us make forward to the ſecond branch of the firſt Exception againſt the baptizing of Children, namely Repentance, the Scripture ſaying, <hi>Repent and be baptized.</hi> This, I hope, will not take us up much time, ſo pray, <hi>Neighbour,</hi> let us to it.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> Thus then object our Adverſaries, and argue upon it, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ought to precede Baptiſm, but Infants cannot repent, and therefore ſhould not be baptized.</p>
            </q>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29431:10"/>
            <p>I anſwer, There are two kinds of Sins (generally ſpeaking) Original and Actual: As to the firſt I ſay, the Obedience of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> is as extenſive as the Prevarication of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and that there are no other means revealed unto us to waſh off this ſtain in Infants but Baptiſm, and ſo moſt reaſonable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that they ſhould, as you have heard before, be Partakers of this Sacrament: but of actual Sins, they being not guilty of thoſe, they have no occaſion to repent.</p>
            <p>So that the Exhortation of St. <hi>Peter, Repent and be baptized,</hi> does not at all concern Infants, but adult Perſons; and this will be undeniable, if we obſerve the occaſion and purport of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe preceding the ſame. So it was, that the Feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> being come, and vaſt numbers of People reſiding then at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to keep the Feaſt, both <hi>Jews</hi> and Proſelites of divers Nations, as <hi>Parthians, Medes, Elamites,</hi> &amp;c. the Apoſtles being met there alſo, and aſſembled together in one of the upper Rooms of the Temple (as their daily cuſtom was) whilſt they were perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divine Service,
<note place="margin">Vid. <hi>Dr.</hi> Hammond <hi>on</hi> Acts 1.13. <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with</hi> cap. 2. ver. 1.</note> it pleaſed Almighty God at that time to pour down upon them the miraculous Gift of the Holy Ghoſt: hereupon they began immediately to ſpeak unto the People in their Maſter's Name, and upon his Buſineſs, in their ſeveral Tongues and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</p>
            <p>The Rumour of this brought a mighty Concourſe to them at the Temple. Now the People finding it even ſo as it was told them, whilſt <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles expounded unto them the Doctrines of the Chriſtian Faith, many of them were convicted in their Conſciences at what they had ſeen and heard, and therefore cried our of a ſudden, <hi>Men and Brethren, What ſhall ue do?</hi> Anſwer was made by <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>Repent, and be baptized in the name of Jeſus Chriſt for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins.</hi> And this plainly ſhews, that Repentance here re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired before Baptiſm was of adult Perſons, whether Jews or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felites (for in this caſe they are all one) that they ſhou'd be heartily ſorry for all the actual Sins they had been guilty of, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to become new Men, and to believe in the Lord Jeſus, that ſo they might be qualified for Baptiſm, the initiating Seal of the Covenant of Faith.</p>
            <p>This is therefore the Apoſtolical Doctrine touching the bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of adult Perſons, they ought to repent and believe, to qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie them for receiving the Seal of the ſaid Covenant: And ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29431:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>far our Mother the Church doth agree with the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> (if this is their Doctrine) as may be ſeen in her Office of Baptiſm of thoſe of riper Years. Thus the Exhortation before it runs: <hi>Save your ſelves from this untoward Generation, for that Baptiſm doth now ſave not by the putting away the filth of the Fleſh, but the anſwer of a good Conſcience.</hi> And the <hi>Rubrick</hi> expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, That due care be taken for the Examination of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as are to be ſo baptiz'd, and that they prepare themſelves with Prayers and Faſting for this holy Sacrament. I need ſay no more on this Head; and I hope this Point will give you no occaſion to leave the Church. Having then agreed thus well in this matter, I ſhall be glad if we can cloſe ſo well in the next Objection, and that is as touching the Manner or Mode of Baptizing.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second General Objection.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>That Dipping, not Sprinkling, is the eſſential and neceſſary Mode of the Sacrament of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to this Objection, I'll not deny any thing herein that Scripture or Antiquity ſeems to favour, as to the cuſtom of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merging or Plunging under Water Perſons to be baptiz'd. 'Tis confeſs'd then, the <hi>Jews</hi> in their proſelyting or making Diſciples by Baptiſm, uſed, I believe, generally to put the Perſons to be baptized all under Water, being conformable to their legal Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations: Thus <hi>Maimonides</hi> ſpeaking of their manner of baptizing, <hi>If any Perſon</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>waſhes or dips himſelf all over but the tip of his little finger, he is yet in his Uncleanneſs.</hi> And if any one had much Hair on his head, that was alſo to be waſhed, elſe the Perſon was reckoned unclean. Suppoſe farther, that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtom, the Mode of <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm was after this manner too, as ſeems to be inferred from his baptizing in <hi>Jordan</hi> and <hi>Enon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.23.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe there was much Water there;</hi> and ſuppoſe farther, that this Cuſtom continued in the Church for ſome time after Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the hot Countries where Dipping of Children might be ſafe as to Cold; and if it be ſo in theſe places (pray ye) who's againſt it?</p>
            <p>What! The Church of <hi>England?</hi> That ſhe is not: for in her <hi>Rubrick</hi> about the Baptizing of Infants, it is thus ordered; That after the Naming of the Child, the Miniſter (if they ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29431:11"/>him the Child may well endure it) ſhall dip it warily in the Water, ſaying, <hi>I baptize thee, &amp;c.</hi> So that you ſee, <hi>Neighbour,</hi> you or any other Perſon might have your Child dipt at its Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm openly at the Font in the Church, if the ſame is deſired. here is therefore no Plea left for your ſeparating from our Church upon this account, unleſs Dipping in the River
<note n="*" place="margin">A <hi>River in the Iſle of</hi> Axholm <hi>in</hi> Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Dipping.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Torn</hi> by a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhall be lookt upon to anſwer better the end of Baptiſm, than Dipping in the Font by a lawful Miniſter.</p>
            <p>But they'll tell you, that Dipping is Eſſential to Baptiſm, and therefore thoſe that have not been dipt have not yet been duly baptized: but this I deny, and let them prove it if they can; and till then, in all reaſon, you ought to ſtand to your former Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. And I make this fair Offer, Do but continue of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion till the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhall be able, from Scripture, Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, or Reaſon, to make appear, that Dipping is eſſentially neceſſary to baptiſm <hi>(ſine quâ non)</hi> and I ſhall deſire your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity no longer.</p>
            <p>Here I might very juſtly lay down my Pen, and at preſent ſay no more, the Authority of the Church (I mean not of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> only, but all or moſt Chriſtian Churches in the Weſtern and Northern parts of the World) now uſing the Sprinkling or Pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water upon Infants at the time of their Baptiſm inſtead of Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of them, is methinks ſufficient Satisfaction to me, and ought to be ſo to any indifferent or unprejudic'd Chriſtian, until the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is made appear, <hi>viz.</hi> That there is an eſſential neceſſity in the very Nature of the Sacrament of Baptiſm, that Immerging or Plunging be the only Mode of Adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>Yet on ſecond Thoughts, when I conſider I am not diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt an Adverſary, as to whom, I ought to take all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable advantage in the way of Argument; but that I am writing to a Pariſhioner, and a Friend, and am endeavouring to ſatisfie one under my Charge in ſome Scruples of Conſcience, which is a Duty incumbent upon my Office, upon this Conſideration <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> I ſhall be free'r with you than otherwiſe I had need to have been, and ſo will give you ſome Reaſons, why I think Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping not eſſentially neceſſary in the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm. And,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. For that I look upon it, there's a vaſt difference to be made betwixt a legal waſhing and a ſacramental one: <hi>John</hi> indeed, in his Baptiſm, doth ſeem to conform to the Jewiſh Mode of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merging; and this Symbol might truly better comport with the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29431:12"/>then preſent Circumſtances of thoſe his Diſciples, who were pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted with an outward, and as it were viſible Stain (as well as an inward one) either of
<note n="*" place="margin">Being grown very corrupt by their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtititious Traditions.</note> 
               <hi>Judaiſm</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſm:</hi> but now (thank God) the caſe is far otherwiſe (the very name of a <hi>Jew</hi> or an <hi>Heathen,</hi> being among us in the Country a ſtrange thing) the Subjects of Baptiſm, generally ſpeaking, are now the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of Chriſtian Parents, and to it there is a promiſory Right or Title included in the Grace of this Covenant:
<note place="margin">Acts 2.39.</note> 
               <hi>The promiſe is to you and your Children,</hi> in whom there remains no legal or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Impurity.</p>
            <p>But now to come to the point in queſtion, why ſhould not a little Water, as well as a great deal, repreſent the inward waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit to Infants at their Baptiſm, who are after a ſort clean before, as being of the ſtock of Believers? So the Apoſtles, <hi>Elſe were your children unclean, but now are they holy.</hi> For inſtance herein, by way of Simile; Was I to ſign you a Bond, would not the impreſs of a little Wax, the bigneſs of my finger's-end, make the Condition of the Bond as good and as ſure unto you, to all intents and purpoſes, as if it had been ſtamp't with a Seal ten times as big? Now in the reaſon of the thing, Why ſhould not a little Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be as good a Seal of the Covenant of Baptiſm, as a greater quantity? and why is not the inward waſhing of the Spirit as vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually repreſented in a ſmall quantity of Water, as well as Chriſt's Body and Blood in a little quantity of Bread and Wine? The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs herein was the Fault of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and juſtly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Apoſtle; but I never underſtood 'twas a Crime to eat or drink ſparingly at the Lord's Table, for that the food there is ſacramental, and the ſtrengthening and refreſhing of our Souls by the Body and Blood of Chriſt is to be lookt at, and not the ſtrengthening of our Bodies by the Bread and Wine: ſhould any think otherwiſe, I muſt ſtop their Mouths with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.22.</note> 
               <hi>Have you not houſes to eat and drink in, or deſpiſe you the Church of God?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So in the other Sacrament we are not ſo much to look at the outward Circumſtances of it <hi>(viz.)</hi> how much or how little Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is neceſſary towards its due Adminiſtration, as to conſider the Deſign and End of it, and not the outward waſhing of the Body of the Perſon baptiz'd, the putting away the filth of the Fleſh (as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks) which might require more or leſs Water for its Purification, according to the Stature, Age, or Uncleanneſs of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29431:12"/>Perſon to be waſh'd: For the uſe of Water in this Sacrament is ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical and repreſentative of the inward waſhing of the Spirit at the time of Adminiſtration;
<note place="margin">Church Cat.</note> 
               <hi>It is an outward viſible ſign of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpiritual Grace, given unto us, and ordained by Chriſt himſelf, as a means whereby we receive the ſame, and a pledge to aſſure us thereof:</hi> and ſo a little Water doth as virtually repreſent the Operation of the Spirit in the new Birth, as well as a little Bread and Wine doth repreſent unto us in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper the Operation of the ſame Spirit in exhibiting to us ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually the Body and Blood of Chriſt, in order to ſtrengthen and confirm in us the new Birth, that we may thereby be enabled to walk in newneſs of Life.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, To this add,</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this very account the</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts <hi>in</hi> Holland <hi>do only pour Water upon or dip the Head.</hi>
               </note> The reaſonableneſs of this Cuſtom being alter'd from Dipping to Sprinkling, (even neceſſity herein compelling;) for in our cold and Northern Climates ſhou'd all the Children (and thoſe are the moſt who want baptizing now) be dip't, well truly they might be ſaid, in a literal ſenſe, to be buried with Chriſt in their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; the waſhing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Regeneration might be the cauſe of ſending them to their Graves. But God loves and delights in Mercy more than in Sacrifice; and therefore that Commiſſion which our Saviour gave in order to the health of our Souls, we cannot, without manifeſt prejudice to the gracious intention of the Lawgiver, ſuppoſe he wou'd have ſo executed as to indanger the health of our Bodies.</p>
            <p>Upon this very Account alſo, we read that the <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> was petitioned, that Dipping in their Female Purgations might be taken away; For what Cauſe? For that the Women of <hi>Galilee,</hi> by reaſon of the Cold they then got, became barren. Did the <hi>Galileans</hi> pity their menſtruous Women, and ſhall not Chriſt have compaſſion of his poor Babes, to whom, when on Earth, he made ſuch kind Promiſes, gave ſuch tender Embraces, and his Divine Bleſſing, and was ſo angry they ſhould be kept from him.</p>
            <p>In fine, I ſhou'd never condemn any Perſon for deſiring to have his Child dip'd; but ſhou'd he ſtand upon it as of the Eſſence of the Sacrament <hi>(ſine quâ non)</hi> that I think would argue his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering too much after the legal and Judaical Waſhings; his put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too much ſtreſs on the outward Element of Water, which is but the viſible Sing; and his ſlighting the thing ſignified, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29431:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>the inward inviſible Grace, the ſecret Waſhing and Purification made by the Spirit at the time of Adminiſtration. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Point with the Judgment of an Ancient Father, when conſulted upon this very account: his words are theſe; <hi>That Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſion in Baptiſm is now generally diſuſed in theſe parts of the World, and Sprinkling ſucceeds in its room, becauſe the tender Bodies of moſt Infants (the only Perſons now to be baptized) could not be put under water in theſe cold Northern Climates without apparent prejudice to their Health, if not their Lives.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this, as in other caſes, God requires Mercy rather than Sacrifice; eſpecially conſidering that the main Ends of Baptiſm are attained this way, and the myſtical Effects thereof, as virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally repreſented by Sprinkling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Dipping. And to this Mode of Baptizing the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> chap. 36. ver. 25, 26. ſeems pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetically to refer, when he ſaith, <hi>Then will I ſprinkle clean Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon you, and ye ſhall be clean from all your Filthineſs; and a new Heart will I give you, and a new Spirit will I put within you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what has been ſaid upon this Head, will, I hope, ſatisfie you <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> and all other Perſons that are not wilfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd againſt Reaſon and Truth: and as for ſuch who are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to diſſent and wrangle on whatever is ſaid or whatever is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, I ſhall adviſe 'em to conſult St. <hi>Paul</hi> for an Anſwer that may be more ſatisfactory; namely, <hi>If any man ſeems to be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, we have no ſuch cuſtom, neither the Churches of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.16.</p>
            <p>And now <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> having gone through the Particulars I was to ſpeak to, and having alſo fairly anſwered ſome of the main Objections our Adverſaries (the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi>) chiefly inſiſt on; I ſhall only leave the whole matter before you in order as it is written, with ſome uſeful Inferences, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>In the Introductory Part of my Letter, I gave you to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that there is ſuch a thing as Men call an Erroneous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and that there is a Zeal ſometimes which is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Knowledge; and hence I infer what a prudent and ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded Chriſtian ought to do, when he had ſome Scruples upon him before he left the Communion of the Church he was in: he ought firſt, from Scripture and Reaſon, to examine into the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidity of the Scruples that ſeem to diſſuade him from his former
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29431:13"/>Profeſſion; and when he has done the beſt he can herein, if his Scruples ſtill grow upon him, before he quits his old way, he ſhou'd then, by all due ways and means examine into the Truth and Safety of the new way propoſed unto him inſtead of the old one, elſe it may ſo happen, that his Change may be for the worſe, and this no wiſe Man wou'd make.</p>
            <p>Now, in the making this Examination, I put you in this way for finding out whether your old Profeſſion or the new propoſed one was the better; I adviſed you to conſult the holy Scriptures (the Standard of Truth) and thereby try your old Religion and your pretended new one, and ſee which of them is purer in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Diſcipline, and Worſhip: and if, upon a Fair hearing of the Cauſe, the old one ſhould prove the better, it would then be clear you ought not in prudence to change; and till this is done, you are to keep to your old way. And,</p>
            <p>For the more orderly trying this Cauſe, our Adverſaries being Complainants, and accuſing our Church of falſe Doctrines, it lies upon them to prove what thoſe Doctrines are, and what be thoſe unlawful Terms of Communion ſhe requires, that are not juſtifiable by the Word of God; and till then we are to keep our Ground, and to act only as Defendants in the Cauſe, no Man being by Law bound to accuſe himſelf. And he that voluntarily eſpouſes a Quarrel againſt the Religion he has been brought up in, without knowing firſt, why and wherefore, acts the part of a weak, not to ſay a contentious, Chriſtian; and 'tis a true Maxim, <hi>He that accuſes another of diſhoneſty, ought to look to himſelf in the firſt place:</hi> Therefore in dealing with our Adverſaries (who are ſo free of their obloquies) I took this Method, purſuant to the proverbial Saying now mentioned, and ſo inquired what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence they have for the Truth; for if they are in the wrong, there's no colour for your joyning with them, what ever there may be for your leaving the Church: for ſuppoſe, for Argument ſake, the way you have been in is not good; yet if the new way you are invited to be worſe, 'tis madneſs to change: ſo that be the Title naught, that in poſſeſſion by the Courteſie of all Laws, is to be look't upon the beſt, and ought to be ſo eſteem'd, until a better is prov'd. In examining then into the Goodneſs and Truth of their Cauſe in Matter of Religion, I took this Method,</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. I gave the Character of thoſe Perſons who were the firſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29431:14"/>Broachers of this Sect of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> and this <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> is a very material thing to be conſidered: For ſuppoſe I had a journey to take of great Conſequence, and being a Stranger to the way, ſome Perſons come, and do very officiouſly offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be my Guide, pretending they underſtand the Road very well, and are making to the ſame place; well ſurely in this caſe, before I give my ſelf up to their Guidance and Conduct, I ſhou'd know who they are, enquire into their character, whether they are <hi>(boni &amp; legales Homines)</hi> honeſt and true Men, and ſhou'd I find them otherwiſe, it wou'd be very madneſs to take them for Guides, let them pretend never ſo fairly: For thus has many an honeſt Man been chouſt out of his Money (and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times his Life too) by the fair Speeches of Thieves and Robbers. In this Caſe, he that values his own ſafety ſhou'd with all ſpeed rid himſelf of their Company, and while he may without ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, bid them adieu. Now,</p>
            <p>To bring this matter home, I have let you know, what the firſt Setters up of this Sect were; when and where it was they cry'd up their ſtupendous Doctrine, <hi>Repent and be re-baptized, or elſe you are damn'd;</hi> what horrid Exploits they play'd, what Barbarous Acts they were guilty of, how they ſack'd and plundred all before them, filling all the places wherever they came with Blood and Confuſion at <hi>Leyden, Munſter, Amſterdam, Utrecht,</hi> and other places. Now this is matter of Fact, and cannot be denied; and pray what think you of theſe new Guides? Is it ſafe to follow them? Did Chriſt and his Apoſtles ever take theſe methods to plant the Doctrines of the Chriſtian Religion? And ſhou'd it be alledged, that the preſent Leaders of the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> are other ſort of Men; I anſwer, Where there are the ſame Principles, there wants nothing but Power and Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to produce the ſame Effects. And this brought me,</p>
            <p n="2">2ly. To conſider what Doctrines they taught. They held that Chriſt was not the true God; to this let them take St. <hi>John</hi>'s anſwer,
<note place="margin">1 John 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>Who is a lyar but he that denyeth that Jeſus is the Chriſt?</hi> He is Antichriſt that denyeth the Father and the Son.</p>
            <p>They taught alſo that we are to be ſaved by our own Merits and Sufferings, and that there is no Original Sin; and this takes away the Merit of our Saviour's Interceſſion, and the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he made on our behalf. They excluded Infants out of the Grace of the Covenant, contrary to our Lord's command, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29431:14"/>them Baptiſm, which is a <hi>Means whereby we receive the ſame, and a Pledge to aſſure us thereof.</hi> They held it lawful for a Man to have more Wives than one; and this ſhews their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinence and Chaſtity; that the godly was to inherit the Earth; and Oaths not to be kept with the Magiſtrate; and this diſcovers their Principles of Civil Government: That any Perſon might take upon him the Miniſterial Office; and this invades our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Authority he left with the Apoſtles and their lawful Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in this behalf. But enough of the Doctrines of this new way.—I went on,</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. And ſhewed that the preſent Methods our Adverſaries uſually take in managing their Cauſe argues that the ſame is naught, for that they are always inveighing againſt the Doctrines or Practice of others, inſtead of proving from Scripture and Reaſon the Truth and Goodneſs of their own way. To this add the great Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (without Reaſon) they have of their Cauſe; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buoy'd-up with Ignorance and Prejudice, what a noiſe and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they make in promoting it, as if they were ſo many <hi>Goliath</hi>'s in arguing, that none could ſtand before them.</p>
            <p>Witneſs the late confident and preſumptuous Challenge they made at <hi>Epworth,</hi> to enter into a publick Diſpute with the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Mr. <hi>Weſly</hi> the preſent Miniſter thereof, who is indeed (the Effect of his good Nature) too civil to them, and too much for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing of their inſolent Behaviour, in confronting the eſtabliſh'd Religion, in Oppoſition and open Defiance to the wholſome Laws of the Land, made and provided for the Honour and Security of the ſame.</p>
            <p>But let me tell them, They who do not value the Peace of the Church, will never regard the Peace of the State: But we deſire no more of their <hi>Munſter</hi>-broyls, occaſioned by their ſeditious Diſputations; therefore 'tis good for them not to uſe their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a cloak of Maliciouſneſs; for if they will ſo far tread in the ſteps of their firſt Reformers as to intrench upon the Authority and kind Indulgence of the Magiſtrate, they muſt be let under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, <hi>that he beareth not the Sword in vain.</hi> And as for their <hi>Goliath</hi>'s Arguments, let them not produce them as is their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſage in a ſeditious and tumultuous manner, where noiſe ſhall prevail above Truth and Reaſon, but in a manly and chriſtian way, and we fear them not; for I do not doubt but when their Locks of Pride and Ignorance (where their boaſted Strength lies) are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29431:15"/>lop'd off, they'll be found in Argument like other Men, and thoſe of the meaneſt Rank too.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>(Neighbour,)</hi> if you will but ſeriouſly conſider the Men, or their Principles, or their manner of ſpreading and abetting of them, I hope you will think it moſt adviſeable to keep to your old way, until a better than this before us is ſhewn you to walk in: and thus we might (as I told you) ſtand our ground, and act only defenſively. But being 'tis the Cauſe of God and Truth, and the deſign of this Letter being not ſo much to aſſail our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as to ſatisfie your Scruples, which if not ſolid, are at leaſt, I believe, well meant; I put the Cauſe ſtill to a fairer Iſſue, and laid before you the Strength of our Adverſaries in the two main Objections.</p>
            <p n="1">1ſt. As to the Objects of Baptiſm.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. As to the manner of its Adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt Objection, I ſhew'd you the Streſs of it lay in this, That Faith and Repentance ſhou'd precede Baptiſm, which Children not being capable of, are not to be baptized: and that none of the force of the Objection ſhould be loſt in the handling of it, I took it in pieces, and ſpoke ſeverally to the Branches of it.</p>
            <p>And firſt, as to Faith, I ſhew'd you by way of parallel, that Circumciſion in the old Teſtament being a Seal of the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Faith, of which Infants were then capable, it muſt needs fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low by parity of Reaſon that Children of Believers under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, muſt be alſo capable of Baptiſm which is the Seal of the New Teſtament, unleſs they will ſuppoſe that the firſt Seal of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant given to <hi>Abraham</hi> was more privilegial and extenſive in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, than the ſecond Seal given by Chriſt. I ſhew'd farther, as matter of Fact, That Children, as well as Men and Women, were always diſcipled by Baptiſm in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, and that Children were included in our Lord's general Commiſſion, they being part of <hi>all Nations:</hi> And that the manner of executing this Commiſſion in all Nations wherever the Chriſtian Faith hath ſpread it ſelf ever ſince the Apoſtles Days, and in all probability in their time alſo doth aſcertain the matter of Fact as to the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing of Infants beyond all denial.</p>
            <p>For matter of Right, I ſhew'd you that Infants have an unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable Title to the thing ſignified, of ſuch being, as our Saviour ſaith, the Kingdom of Heaven, who can queſtion their having a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29431:15"/>right to the ſign? beſides that the Promiſe is to you and your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and that the promiſſory Grace in the Sacrament is no ways letted by the perſonal Incapacity of the Recipient, for that a King may be crown'd in a Cradle, and become really King, though he knows not of it; and many Kindneſſes may be actually done to Infants, by their Parents, Friends, or Guardians, though they are not privy to it; and however at the leaſt, Children now of believing Parents are every whit as capable of the Seal of Baptiſm as the Children of the <hi>Jews</hi> were of the Seal of Circumciſion, as was before declar'd, and for the Reaſons there alledged.</p>
            <p>As to the ſecond branch of their firſt Exception, <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhew'd you very plainly, that it concerns adult Perſons only; for Infants having not been guilty of actual Sins, there is no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for their actual Repentance; and as for Perſons of riper Years (if they're not baptized till then) we do agree they ought firſt to believe; for it would be moſt unreaſonable to admit an adult Perſon Chriſt's Diſciple, who did not firſt believe in him and acknowledge him for his Saviour; and that there is alſo in theſe a neceſſity of Repentance; for ſuch having been alſo guilty of actual Sins, they ought and muſt repent of them, before they are capable of this Sacrament which is the Laver of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and he that puts on Chriſt muſt become a New Creature. I came then,</p>
            <p>To the ſecond general Objection relating to the Mode of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and did ſo far agree, that Dipping was probably the manner of baptizing in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, and that the ſame was likely ſo too in <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm; but then I ſhew'd you there was at that time a particular Reaſon for this Mode of baptizing, for that the Perſons then to be baptized had, as it were, a viſible, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Uncleanneſs upon them, namely <hi>Judaiſm</hi> or <hi>Heatheniſm.</hi> I agree farther, that this Cuſtom was probably in uſe in hot Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries ſome time after Chriſt and his Apoſtles, where the ſame might be done without endangering the Health of the baptized: and I ſhew'd you alſo that our Church is not againſt this uſe when it may be done with fafety, as appears by her <hi>Rubrick</hi> of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
            <p>But then to urge, that this Mode of dipping is Eſſential in the very nature of the Sacrament, that I deny'd, and put it to the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> to prove it if they could; and did ſay, and do ſay ſtill, that a little Water in Baptiſm, by ſprinkling or pouring the ſame
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29431:16"/>upon the Perſon baptized, doth as virtually and ſacramentally exhibit the Seal of the Covenant, as the greateſt quantity whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; even as I ſhew'd you by the like parity of Reaſon, that a little Bread and Wine, the leaſt Sup, as well as the biggeſt Draught, in the other Sacrament, doth ſufficiently repreſent the Body and Blood of Chriſt to every worthy Communicant; and hereupon did urge farther, that for any Perſon to inſiſt upon Dipping as eſſential to the Sacrament of Baptiſm, it ſeem'd to me to be a leaning too much to the Judaical Waſhings, and putting too much ſtreſs upon the outward Sign (the Element of Water) and a ſlighting the thing ſignified, the inward waſhing and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible operations of the Spirit. I ſhew'd you what was the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an ancient Father of the Church when conſulted on this occaſion, and what was and is the Practice of all, or moſt, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches in the Weſtern and Northern parts of the World: and now in the cloſe I ſhall refer the whole matter of this Letter to your ſerious and Chriſtian Conſideration, with this Caution on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.14.</note> that you bear always in mind, in the peruſal of it, St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Advice to <hi>Timothy; Of theſe things put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord, that they ſtrive not about words to no profit, but to the ſubverting of the hearers.</hi> To conclude,</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> you ſee, upon due enquiry made, there's really nothing in the new way we have been ſpeaking of to invite you to it, unleſs Principles of Sedition, Hereſie and Schiſm, can be any due Motives herein. No, the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> poſitively affirms, that they who upon this account cauſe Diviſions in the Church of God, are ſuch as love not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but that by their <hi>good words and fair ſpeeches they deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.18.</note> Pray then, be not led away with an outward ſhew of pretended Sanctity and Holineſs, for ſuch a Vizard the falſe Teachers were to put on. 'Tis our Saviour's own Affirmation, that there ſhould ariſe <hi>falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets,</hi> who ſhould be ſo artful in their counterfeit ſhews of Piety, as to go near impoſing upon the very Favourites of Heaven, the Elect or choſen of God.
<note place="margin">Mat. 24.24, 25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Take therefore our Lord's Advice herein; <hi>If they ſhall ſay unto thee, he is in the deſart, go not forth: behold, he is in the ſecret chamber, believe it not.</hi> For when the Root is unſound, the Branches muſt be ſo likewiſe: A corrupt Tree may bring forth Fruit fair to the eye, but not really good. Where the Doctrines
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29431:16"/>of any Sect are againſt God's Word (as 'tis plain the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> are) they are none of Chriſt's, let them pretend what they will. Hear what our Lord bids us do in this caſe; <hi>Judge not according to the appearance, but judge righteous judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as there is nothing in the new way, things rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, to invite you to it, ſo you have heard there is nothing in the old way, the good old Religion you have been baptized and brought up in, to diſſuade you from it. All the Objections our Adverſaries have yet made are vaniſh'd, and fled as Chaff before the Wind. Truth is great, and will prevail. If you are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Lover of God and of Chriſt, of Truth and of your own Soul, hold faſt to your former Profeſſion without wavering, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt give you a right Underſtanding in all things.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Which is the ſincere and hearty Prayer of Your loving Friend and Miniſter,</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Hatfield,</hi> 
                  <date>Jan. 19. 1699/1700.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Eratt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29431:17"/>
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Am told <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> by ſeveral, that you ſeem concern'd, for that you hear I'm angry at you. Now to be free with you, and that you may have no more occaſion to liſten to Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, I tell you frankly I am in ſome meaſure really ſo: but that I may not be miſunderſtood in this, you muſt give me leave herein to expreſs my own Meaning; and this is but common Juſtice, every Man being ſuppos'd the beſt Interpreter of his own words.</p>
               <p>In order then that you or any other Perſon may the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand my Meaning when I ſay <hi>I am angry at you,</hi> I ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the matter two ways, with regard to an unjuſt or a juſt Anger: and the Word bears theſe two ſenſes in the common Uſage of it, and ſo 'tis alſo taken in Holy Writ. To theſe I ſhall ſpeak a little ſeverally.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to unjuſt Anger, taken in a ſtrict ſenſe, it imports, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſpeaking, not ſo much an Evil, as a groundleſs and haſty Paſſion. The former of theſe our Saviour condemns, when he tells us,
<note place="margin">Matt. 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>We muſt not be angry with our Brother without a cauſe;</hi> of the latter I take the elder Son in the Goſpel to be guilty; for though his Anger, with regard to his prodigal Brother, might not be altogether groundleſs, yet was it too raſh and haſty.</p>
               <p>The Thoughts of his Brother having waſted his Father's Goods in riotous living, gave cauſe of juſt Reſentment; but then the conſideration of his being reform'd, of his becoming a new Man, of his being return'd home in his Perſon, but not in his Vices, which moved the tenderneſs of a Father to pardon, ſhould alſo, if it had been well conſidered, have prevail'd with the Brother too not to have been angry: the greater Good ſhou'd have out-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced the leſſer Evil; and ſo the occaſion of the Father's Mirth ſhou'd have ſtirr'd up Joy in the Brother alſo, and not a fretting Paſſion, being grounded upon this ſolid Reaſon, <hi>For this thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was dead and is alive again,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 15.28, 32.</note> 
                  <hi>was loſt and is found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am, alas! too much Man to clear my ſelf of having been never guilty of both theſe two fooliſh Paſſions, a Groundleſs and Haſty Anger; and, to take up the words of holy <hi>Job, Should I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:29431:17"/>juſtifie my ſelf herein, my own mouth would condemn me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 9.20.</note> No, far be that Preſumption from me; but I muſt freely with the Apoſtle own my ſelf <hi>of like Paſſions with other men.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 14.15.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now as to the latter inſtance of an haſty Paſſion, I wiſh I might with the elder Brother be blam'd and condemn'd by all good Men, ſhou'd I be angry when I ought to rejoyce if my ſtraying Brother who was loſt ſhould be found and return home. And ſo much for unjuſt Anger in the aforementioned reſpects.</p>
               <p>But then there's an unjuſt Anger which goes farther, and may come within the Verge of a malicious Temper. Now ſhould any be ſo uncharitable as to inſinuate from my ſaying <hi>I was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at you,</hi> that I maliciouſly intended you an ill turn, the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of it might be ſuppoſed one of theſe two things; either it was in prejudice to your Perſon, or in pique to the Sect of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> which you ſeem inclining to: As to both which, I thus apologize for my ſelf.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to a malicious Temper: I appeal to all my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, whether ever my Carriage or Behaviour among them has deſerv'd ſuch a Cenſure. That I have been ever ready upon all occaſions to ſerve my Pariſhioners, and to do them any kindneſs that lay in my power, I promiſe my ſelf ſo much, that every one of them (not excepting <hi>John Woodward</hi>) wou'd (if need require) averr in my behalf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to any bitterneſs of Spirit towards Diſſenters from the Church, with that I hope none can juſtly charge me; and I put the Queſtion to your ſelf, Whether all the laſt Year, in your Converſe with me (when Church-warden) you ever at any time heard me rail againſt any Perſons whatſoever that differ'd with me in point of Religion. (This then being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed,)</p>
               <p>I muſt tell you there's a great difference to be made betwixt one who has all his Life-time been brought up a Diſſenter (whom Education and Cuſtom has ſo far blinded that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not eaſily, if he would, diſcern and embrace the Truth) and a Perſon that out of an unadviſed and wilful Humour runs away from the Church, and knows not <hi>Why</hi> or <hi>Wherefore.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29431:18"/>
               <p>The firſt is an Infirmity, and is really to be pitied; the other is a Diſeaſe, and ſo proper means are to be made uſe of in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a Cure. Now in this caſe, all gentle Methods are firſt to be taken; and he muſt be reckon'd an unwiſe or an unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſician, that ſhou'd do otherwiſe: but if all this is done, and the Diſeaſe ſtill grows worſe and worſe, turns to a malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Diſtemper, and threatens Danger to the Publick,</p>
               <p>In ſuch an Extremity, when the Infection cannot be cured, it has always been thought adviſable to ſhut up or remove the Perſon infected, though never ſo near a Friend. And I think I may herein, without being guilty of a Droll or lightneſs of Expreſſion in ſo ſerious a matter as is now before us, apply the common Proverb, which is as true as plain, <hi>That one ſcabb'd Sheep may infect a whole Flock.</hi> But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. There's a juſt Anger. And of this ſort we have ſufficient Examples in Holy Writ; and thus <hi>Jacob</hi> did juſtly reſent <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel</hi>'s too forward Petition, <hi>Give me children, or elſe I die;</hi> as if that Bleſſing had been abſolutely in the Power of Man; and therefore <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Anger was kindled againſt <hi>Rachel,</hi> (though 'tis known he loved her well) and he ſaid, <hi>Am I in God's ſtead? who has withheld from thee the fruit of the womb?</hi> Geneſis 30. ver. 1, 2.</p>
               <p>And ſo was <hi>Moſes</hi> juſtly diſpleaſed at <hi>Korah</hi> and his Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for their preſumptuous uſurping the Prieſt's Office, and private tampering with the People, to ſet them a murmuring againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> their Governour and their Prieſt.</p>
               <p>Thus did our Bleſſed Saviour unkindly reſent the Abuſe of the Temple, the Houſe of Prayer, in the Peoples profaning of it by their merchandizing in the ſame; his Words and his Actions ſhew this: <hi>He caſt out them that bought and ſold in the Temple, and overthrew the tables of the money-changers, and the ſeats of them that ſold doves, ſaying, my houſe ſhall be called of all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the houſe of Prayer, but ye have made it a den of Thieves,</hi> Mark 11.15, 17.</p>
               <p>And thus is God Almighty ſaid to be angry with his People, when they offend either by their Words or Actions. And to give you another Inſtance; When the People, out of a pretence of greater Holineſs, diſſented from the publick Worſhip, made
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29431:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>their private Sacrifices, and offered ſtrange Incenſe. Now as to the Crime, and how God Almighty reſented it, hear from his own Word; <hi>I have ſpread out my hands all the day unto a rebellious People which walketh in a way that was not good,</hi> (after their own Thoughts) <hi>a People that provoketh me to Anger con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to my face</hi> (and how was this?) <hi>that ſacrificeth in Gardens and burneth Incenſe upon brick, which ſay, Stand by thy ſelf, come not near to me, for I am holier than thou: theſe are a ſmoak in my noſe, and a fire that burneth all day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From what has been urged on this Head I infer, That in ſome caſes there is a very juſt Anger. Thus Magiſtrates may, and ought, ſharply to reprehend all ſeditious and villainous Practices. So alſo Parents diſobedient Children, Maſters un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Servants, and the Miniſters of God's Word ought to tell the People under their charge of their Faults: <hi>Cry aloud and ſpare not</hi> (ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 58. ver. 1.) <hi>ſhew my People their tranſgreſſions,</hi> (and theſe related to Errours in Principles as well as Practice:) ſo I alſo as a Miniſter of the Goſpel (though one, God knows, the unworthieſt of my Brethren) do think I fall a ſhare in this Authority or Power of reprehending Errours in my Pariſhioners, whether of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or otherwiſe.</p>
               <p>And in this Caſe, and upon this Account, I am angry with you, who having lived ſo long in the Communion of our Church, who the very laſt Year performed the Office of <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden,</hi> and I muſt needs ſay, did, I believe, according to your Oath, and the beſt of your Knowledge, honeſtly diſcharge your ſelf herein; who was the ſame Year confirmed by the Biſhop, and did then, (if you underſtood your Duty therein) renew your Baptiſmal Vow, and promiſe to remain ſtedfaſt in your holy Profeſſion. Add to this, your frequent receiving the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Lord's Supper, which is or ought to be the Seal of our Confirmation in the Faith and Doctrines of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now for you to have done all this, and as ſoon as ever you was out of Office of <hi>Church-warden,</hi> to run away from the Church, from your Baptiſm, from the late ſolemn Confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, from the Communion with your Brethren at the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29431:19"/>Lord's Table, and never to tell your Miniſter <hi>Why</hi> or <hi>Wherefore</hi> you did it, is to me very unaccountable; as if the Profeſſion of our Church was ſo groundleſs and ſo deſpicable, that nothing cou'd be ſaid for it worth your regarding.</p>
               <p>But now to ſee how the Caſe is alter'd is admirably ſtrange: You are already more civil to your new way; witneſs what you ſaid Yeſterday at Mr. <hi>Pryms,</hi> among your Neighbours; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That did I come, you had nothing to ſay to me: but, if I pleas'd, one of your Teachers ſhould give me a meeting, and diſpute it out with me. In the name of Goodneſs what a ſhame is it, that you ſhould already be ſo muffled and blinded, as to pin your Faith on another Man's ſleeve!</p>
               <p>It not this plain Confeſſion, you have forſaken your old way, and taken a new one, and you know not <hi>Why</hi> or <hi>Wherefore.</hi> This is not according to the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Rule, which bids us <hi>be ready always to give an anſwer to every man that ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth you the reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekneſs and fear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It had indeed been a decent and modeſt Anſwer, with regard to your old Profeſſion you had ſo long liv'd in, had you told your new Teachers thus: <hi>Sirs, before I turn, you muſt give me leave to adviſe firſt with my own (or ſome more able) Miniſter, and then you ſhall hear farther from me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to ſay, with reſpect to your new way, You refer me to your Teachers, diſcovers the Sandineſs of the Foundation you build upon: 'Tis a Popiſh Principle, and argues an implicit Faith. This very plainly ſhews, that you are become one of thoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of when he thus declares,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The time ſhall come when Men will not endure ſound Doctrine, but after their own luſts ſhall heap to themſelves Teachers, having itching ears: And they ſhall turn away their ears from the Truth, and ſhall be turn'd to fables,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.3, 4.</p>
               <p>I cannot but farther take notice of the indecent, not to ſay cenſorious, Expreſſion that you left me laſt night as a bone to pick on; viz. <hi>That you would ſtay no longer, for that you loved not the works of darkneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pray what do you mean? If you ſpeak it with reſpect to me, I deſire to know what are thoſe black and helliſh Deeds you have to lay to my charge: A God's-name ſpeak out, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:29431:19"/>no more than you know is true, and I ask you no Indulgence.</p>
               <p>But if you would inſinuate into my People a Belief of things that are falſe, this I muſt needs ſay is neither Chriſtian nor fair dealing.</p>
               <p>If by the <hi>Works of Darkneſs</hi> you meant, that I, which regard to my Profeſſion, am a <hi>blind Guide,</hi> and ſo thoſe that follow me, like Men i'th' dark, muſt fall in the Ditch.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, That I believe thoſe of my Pariſhioners who were with me laſt Night, and heard what I ſaid, did not think ſo. I add farther, however the Cauſe I have taken upon me to juſtify may ſuffer by my Weakneſs or Inability in its Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>I muſt tell you, the Light of the Church you have left, and ſo much deſpiſe, will ſhine bright as the Sun in the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when your new Lamp, having ſpent all its droſſy Oyl, ſhall be quite extinguiſh'd, and leave only an unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſmell behind it; ſhall vaniſh in Smoak and Stench.</p>
               <p>Now to prevent your raſh cenſuring after this manner for the future, a Talent peculiar and remarkable in the Sect you are inclining to. I adviſe you to bear in mind what the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>Why doſt thou judge thy Brother? or why doſt thou ſet at naught thy Brother? for we ſhall all ſtand before the Judment ſeat of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe things conſider'd, I cannot but think I've a juſt Cauſe to reſent and be angry at your too forward and indiſcreet Zeal. But then,</p>
               <p>By way of Apology in your behalf, I conſider alſo <hi>(Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum eſt errare)</hi> Miſtake is a common Infirmity, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a Chriſtian Compaſſion and Forbearance, ſo that a Man does not perſiſt wilfully in his Faults; for when any one's Errours are detected, he ought and muſt own and forſake them: and the doing this is ſo far from being a ſhame, that 'tis Manly and Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>Pray then <hi>(Neighbour)</hi> do not tye up your Reaſon and your Conſcience, but give your ſelf the freedom of Thinking and Judging, the only diſtinguiſhing Character of a reaſonable Man. 'Tis yet in your power to do your ſelf and your Church Juſtice: and I have already learn'd from St. <hi>Paul</hi> how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have my ſelf towards a penitent Offender; <hi>Brethren, if any Man
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:29431:20"/>be overtaken in a fault, ye which are ſpiritual, reſtore ſuch a one in the Spirit of Meekneſs, conſidering thy ſelf, leſt thou alſo be tempted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What remains, but to beg of God to give you Grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home; and me your Miniſter, and all your Brethren, my Pariſhioners, Grace alſo to receive you again as we ought. Which is the unfeigned prayer of,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>From</hi> Valkenburgh-Hall <hi>in the</hi> Levels, <date>
                        <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1699.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Yours as before, <hi>W. E.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29431:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
